‘Life is for living’, according to the well-used expression: What we choose to do is up to us.
有句老生常谈的话是这么说的：“人生在世，就要活出精彩”。我们选择过怎样的生活，全凭自己做主。
That may not be completely true, but there is no harm in dreaming about what we’d like to achieve in our life.
这话或许并非完全正确，但畅想一下自己毕生想要实现的目标，总归是无伤大雅的。
Many of us write a list of things we’d like to do before we die – often called a bucket list.
很多人都会写下一份“人生愿望清单”，罗列自己离世前想做的事。
Bucket lists have been called ‘the greatest hits of your life’ and have helped some people overcome anxiety which would have stopped them following their dreams.
人生愿望清单被称为“人生中的高光时刻清单”，它帮助一些人克服了阻碍他们追逐梦想的焦虑情绪。
Some of us may choose to write one to fill our life with exciting and new experiences – from skydiving to swimming with sharks – the list is unlimited.
有些人会选择列这样一份清单，让生活充满新奇刺激的体验——从高空跳伞到和鲨鱼同游，清单上的内容可以无穷无尽。
This is something the BBC radio programme All In The Mind has been looking at.
英国广播公司电台节目《心灵深处》就探讨过这个话题。
It heard from a blogger called Annette White who said she made a promise to live her bucket list which “continuously pushes the comfort zone to its limits and beyond it.”
节目采访了博主安妮特·怀特，她表示自己下定决心要完成人生愿望清单，这份清单“不断将舒适区推向极限，甚至突破极限”。
Such a list can be exciting and can indeed help you plan your life and give you focus.
这样的清单能让人满怀期待，也确实能帮你规划人生、明确方向。
When the BBC reporter Helen Fawkes knew she was suffering from incurable ovarian cancer, she took comfort in drawing up a bucket list - although she called it her ‘list for living’ because these were things for making the most of life.
英国广播公司记者海伦·福克斯在得知自己患上了无法治愈的卵巢癌后，从拟定人生愿望清单这件事里获得了慰藉——不过她把这份清单称为“人生清单”，因为清单上的事情都是为了充分享受生活。
Sadly, she was not able to achieve all of her 50 things before she died at the age of 45.
令人惋惜的是，在她45岁离世前，没能完成清单上的全部50件事。
Creating a bucket list can certainly give us hope, but some people have argued it can be used as a coping strategy to try to control something uncontrollable – death.
拟定人生愿望清单固然能给我们带来希望，但也有人认为，这不过是一种应对策略，试图去掌控一些无法掌控的东西——比如死亡。
Clinical psychologist Linda Blair told the BBC that she was “not really in favour of bucket lists… [they] take you away from the chance to be spontaneous.”
临床心理学家琳达·布莱尔在接受英国广播公司采访时表示，她“并不太赞成人生愿望清单……这类清单会让你错失随性而为的机会”。
It’s probably true that a list can encourage people to follow someone else’s idea of the perfect life.
确实，清单可能会促使人们去追逐别人眼中的完美人生。
And also, following a fixed list of goals makes you less impulsive - your aims and wishes might change as you approach the day when you finally kick the bucket.
而且，照着一份固定的目标清单行事，会让你变得不再随性——当你离人生终点越来越近时，你的目标和心愿或许也会随之改变。
But why not at least dream of what we would like to do?
但我们至少可以畅想一下自己想做的事，不是吗？
Why not reach for the stars, even if we only reach the sky?
为什么不心怀高远、奋力追梦呢？即便最终没能实现目标，至少也努力过。
Whether we want to plan it or just see what happens, we don’t know what tomorrow will bring, so maybe we should live for today.
无论我们是想规划人生，还是选择顺其自然，都要知道，未来充满未知，或许我们应该活在当下。